All right, party on.
Thank you everyone for being here.
Today we're going to talk about the edge, one term that is bubbling around in the infrastructure
world and one that keeps a lot of people with tons of excitement.
My name is Chase Roberts.
I'm an investor at Vertex Ventures.
We're an early stage venture capital firm that invests in technical founders building
enterprise software companies.
I've got my colleague Megan here as well.
Megan say hello.
Hey.
Awesome.
And then with that, why don't we, we've got a fantastic panel.
So why don't we start with some introductions?
If everyone could say their name, what they're working on, and then we're going to add one
more spicy question, which is what was the first technology that you ever loved or have
any memory of loving?
So why don't we start with Guillermo and then we'll go to Kurt and then Nick.
Hey everybody.
Thanks for this opportunity Chase and Megan.
I'm really excited to talk about the edge today.
So I'm Guillermo Rauch.
I'm the creator of Next.js and the CEO and founder of Purcell, the platform that enables
developers to create and deploy their dreams onto the web.
And the first technology that you remember loving?
Great question by the way.
Love it.
It made me really think back to my childhood.
And one of the things I always mentioned is that for me, open source really started it
all.
And the first technology that I really fell in love with was Linux and in particular the
Debian Linux distribution.
It had the caveat that it was slightly harder to install to what I was using before, which
was Red Hat, which had a very consumer focus in the beginning.
So Debian was like, I felt like a hacker.
I loved apt-get and apt-cache search, just like installing packages, spending time on
the terminal.
I really, really loved it.
And it really consumed a lot of my childhood.
It became one with the technology.
I freaking loved it.
So thanks for bringing it back to memory.
That's great.
How about you, Kurt?
I'm Kurt.
I'm CEO and one of the founders of Fly.io.
We're a dev-focused cloud for running full stack apps all over the world, close to the
users.
If I go away, this is going to age me.
My favorite, my formative technology was actually, it was 3D Studio release 4, which is notable
because it was the last one for MS-DOS before they switched to Windows and became 3D Studio
Max.
And it was the, at that point it convinced me I wanted to go work at Pixar and animate
movies for the rest of my life.
It was the 3D animation package.
I'm not actually very good at 3D animation or modeling, but I could do some stuff.
And I liked how it ended up looking.
So it's the first time I remember like making something and then being able to show it to
people, which was a very, that stuck with me.
I still like to do that.
It's weird.
That's cool.
And then alternative universe, Kurt, is accepting a, not a Grammy, an Oscar for some digital
...
Probably a Razzie.
It definitely would be a Razzie.
Nice.
And last and certainly not least, Nick.
Appreciate it.
Thanks.
So my name's Nick.
I am the VP of engineering at PlanetScale.
So we're a database as a kind of a service platform built to help you get from zero to
what we say outrageous scale, really bigger than you can fathom.
And the first technology, my formative technology was the M IRC scripting language for those
of you who are here with IRC.
I really loved, you know, when I was a kid, being able to dial up onto the internet and
kind of chat with strangers was like the pinnacle of the internet.
And I really wanted to start doing was write bots and scripts and stuff like that to make
that more fun.
So I taught myself how to write M IRC scripting language from cobbling together random snippets
from the internet.
That was the first time I ever felt like, you know, I was actually building something
on the internet and doing something.
And yeah, I think Kurt, that time from zero to I've got something to show someone one
of the best parts about technology, when you can minimize that and just do something special,
you know, right from your laptop.
That's amazing.
Well, I will not share mine because mine is not nearly as interesting as those and it
may or may not have had something to do with customizing my Myspace page.
But with that, why don't we go ahead and kick this off by actually defining the edge.
This term could mean a lot of different things to a lot of different people.
So it'd be interesting just to go around the group and like actually work out a definition
here.
So, you know, perhaps we'll start with Guillermo again.
Like how would you define the edge?
Like what is this thing?
Yeah, a couple of thoughts there.
One that's really quick and relevant to the Vercel mission, which is to make the web faster
and more personalized.
I think of the edge fundamentally as a means to an end.
It's infrastructure that's necessary in an increasing number of ways to get to that goal
of making the web faster and more personal.
But on a technical level, I would define it in the way we implement it is a very fast
cloud native way of running code as close as possible to the visitor.
But I think the crucial distinction here is that not really on their device.
A lot of folks from like the IOT wave and prior, I think what makes the edge word a
little confusing to some folks sometimes is some folks may say like edge is the Kubernetes
cluster that runs inside Chipotle and if you all heard about that story.
To us at Vercel is you deploy and we run it in data centers as close as possible to the
user.
Maybe one day we'll get to Chipotle, but right now it's in the major areas next to visitors
where we'll serve really fast e-commerce experiences, marketing experiences, dashboards, consoles
and to your point, Chase, the need really is coming from the point of view of acceleration.
We have a, there's a lot of, we're going to use a lot of the same words here, I think.
And I like the IOT call out.
I think when we talk about edge, which is rare, we almost actually, we don't say edge
very often, but I think when in general we're talking about edge, we started to think about
it as almost like there's kind of like two sides of the edge and what Guillermo is talking
about and where we work, I think is on like, we call it the trusted side of the edge, which
is like, it's basically like compute we own that's close to people.
And so one, I love the Chick-fil-A Kubernetes call out because it's one of the most fascinating
thing, like an otherwise boring company has ever done, which it's worth Googling about
if you're not aware of it.
And then, but one of the, it's interesting to me how like the company is doing edge stuff
that people seem to care about are largely talking about like kind of compute you own
and trust where it's almost like multi-tenant compute resources.
You don't necessarily let everyone access it without some kind of off and like isolation
versus IOT, the stuff that's on the other side where it's like the untrusted side of
the edge.
And so, yeah, we think about it basically the same.
We just have this notion of trusted versus not, and we don't pay attention to the untrusted.
Before I pass it to Nick, I want to ask a question about the compute you own and trust.
Like how is that different than having a data center?
I'll back up.
When I was at Box, I remember one of our customers was evaluating, you know, moving to the cloud
and one of the soon to be customers, and they took us to their data center, which was just
above the cafeteria.
And they're like, yeah, we're basically like one spilled pot of oil in a fire away from
just losing all of our data.
But theoretically that's data that sits close to them, or compute that sits close to them
that they own.
So like, what's the difference here?
Oh, nothing.
I think that nobody wants to talk about that.
But like every data center on the planet is, you know, there's that kind of story.
And even when they build them to be all redundant and smart and on two power grids, there's
still some dude with like, you know, a nice stick leaning against the back door, propping
it open, but making sure no one goes in.
I think when like the one maybe like intrinsic difference, if you're building things for
the edge is you end up almost being kind of redundant by default.
So you become a little bit more resilient to coffee spills.
We see this actually with S3, we do a tremendous amount of access to S3, specifically in the
U.S. East one, which is Virginia.
And it's actually incredibly flaky all over the world.
And some of the, some of like what edge applications have been able to do is like, you'll see that
S3 stops working from Frankfurt.
And what can happen is like the health checks there can just stop working and traffic will
just route around Frankfurt at that point.
So if you imagine that S3 is a spilled coffee, you can kind of, you can kind of be a little
bit more resilient to that.
But I feel like that's like a, it's like a side effect of doing things this way.
It's not necessarily the reason you would move out of your one sketchy, grippy data
center.
I would add there's two adjacent concepts that get thrown into the same edge umbrella.
One really is what Kurt just said about resilience that comes from deploying globally by default,
being global first, right?
So when you come to a platform like Vercel, you're not really, we're not starting the
conversation by what region are you deploying in today?
And like switching dashboard context with like a city on the top right of the dashboard,
it's like something that comes with it, with the concept of deploying your workload globally.
But then the flip side of that too, is sometimes certain workloads do need to be co-located
to the data store as well.
So I think something that comes with this edge platforms is that flexibility with a
bias towards global, right?
So at the end of the day, there is a reality of sometimes the computer needs to live right
next to the data.
That's where I think all of us see more stress and more workloads in Virginia still, because
there's still a lot of gravity there, but I think we're opening the aperture to every
company by default to think about catering to visitors as close as possible to them and
co-locating our apps to them.
Totally.
You know, and I heard this on Twitter, I don't remember who tweeted it, so if you're going
to take credit, feel free.
But the way I think about the edge is if you draw a string, you've got a user, you've got
kind of the app server serving their requests, and maybe you've got the data stores that
are powering their request.
And historically, right, no matter where kind of the user was, they had this distance to
the application server that was longer depending on how far away they went.
Sure, you could slide it closer to some users, you could slide it farther away to get closer
to other users.
So you may be in the US East for kind of acceptable latency to California and to Europe.
You may be in Europe and have terrible latency to the West Coast of the United States, but
you kind of made that trade off with one string.
When you add in edge compute, you gain the ability to have a string per user, and sometimes
you can make that incredibly short.
So if you've got someone on a mobile device, you can have a 10, 15, 20 millisecond server
right away from them that can render their dashboard or that can load their information
incredibly fast.
And while this isn't a new concept, people always say the cloud is just someone else's
data center, well, the edge is just 75 of someone else's data centers.
Kind of the patterns and the abilities that we provide developers to be able to start
off with this by default, just makes the base case so much better than it was 10 years ago,
where you'd pick one, you'd build up all this gravity.
And I remember other companies I worked at, you'd say, well, to just add a second one
is like a monumental task.
We're going to rewrite the whole application.
The edge stops you from, you know, the edge pattern stops you from having to start off
under the assumption that you'll have to do that later on.
I love that visualization.
So I'm here in SF and say the app service in Virginia.
So I have one little dot in that string that is, okay, the distance between me and Virginia.
But now with edge compute, another notch that I would add to that visualization is I can
also place compute close to the visitor, even though I might still go to the origin to do
some of my compute.
So to bring this into a more concrete example, we have this product called edge middleware.
And what it's allowing folks to do is to progressively adopt the edge by hoisting some of the computation
close to the visitor.
So a lot of that routing layer, a lot of that AB testing, a lot of that load balancing,
we see a lot of incremental migration patterns to this new world of front end driven workloads
to headless where the customer might say, I'm going to use edge middleware.
I'm going to put compute right next to every visitor globally, and I'm gonna start distributing
the workloads.
So maybe most of my pages fall back to my old legacy model list, but the new ones go
to my new application that I'm developing.
And they're making that determination, that policy is being pushed to the edge.
That might not be where the story ends.
There might be more compute elsewhere down the pipe, but now they got that extra lever
and that extra knob.
Great example.
We actually use this in our product with Vercel.
Every time we have an incident, we have a nice little status that pops up right next
to the database page to make sure people know if they're experiencing issues.
We want to give them that information ASAP.
That's actually a Vercel edge middleware that goes back and calls our incident API and caches
the data for 10, 20 seconds.
So that pops up extremely quickly served very close to the user on a very short string.
Whereas the big heavy operations may go back to our kind of, let's say bigger database
servers over here, but we're able to get that and kind of decorate the page with that information
in an extremely low latency way.
That is a great experience for users.
Maybe digging deeper here, what are the key use cases that you're seeing driving Edge
Infra today?
Maybe Nick, maybe continue with your thought.
Yeah, no, and I think it's really similar to what I'm talking about.
It's a fantastic question.
Sometimes I think it's 50%, just the default way of doing things now, you know, you're
looking at it and you think, well, if I've got users all over the globe, the internet
is increasingly global.
You know, we're, we're selling, you know, you look at Facebook users, you look at these
big social media companies, the primary largest number of users are not in the United States
anymore.
They're in India, they're in, you know, all over.
And so you're looking at this and when you're a developer starting out, you think what's
the best way that I can serve that global audience.
Why would you pick something worse?
And so you're looking at being able to get data stores, applications, and build tools
that just work with that foundation from day one.
And if you can do that, if you can kind of build that in from the ground up, you never
have to worry about adding it back on.
So I think half of it is honestly just, it's the best thing to build the best product.
The other half of it, I think is just frankly, even performance.
Then we spend so much time of our lives optimizing five milliseconds here, 10 milliseconds here,
the edge paradigm can cut 20, 50%, 75% of a request just kind of by opting in.
And that's like handy to a baby.
You know, you're like, why wouldn't I try and go get that better page load time, that
faster documentation site.
That's what we spend our lives optimizing and the edge just makes it so much easier.
We see a, I think a similar thing and I've sort of, if you imagine like kind of game
features and apps, what's been interesting to me is how many people want to build things
that look vaguely like game features into even like boring line of business applications.
And it's because we all, at this point of like we use discord and we look at things
like Excalidraw, right?
And Figma, and we all know how these things work.
And I think there's this developer emotion where it's like, I could imagine how to apply
like this kind of trick to this internal invoicing site I'm having to build at my day job.
And so that pushes a little bit of that where you'd like, there are reasons to have really
quick interactions with the server outside of a page view.
And a lot of it is kind of driven by those gamified features.
And I think that some of it is it's the default because this is the right way to do this for
the types of apps people want to build, which actually makes probably all of our lives much
easier at this point than it would have been like five years ago.
But it's a lot of it's really neat to watch developers like discover a way of doing things
and then influence the world to make it possible, which seems to be what's happening right now.
Yeah, to add to that, I think what drives a lot of that developer inclination to use
edge is also that modern frameworks are becoming edge first as well.
So Next.js, Astro, Remix, all the frameworks for building for the web are also agreeing
that if we want to drive performance, if we want to drive personalization, they have to
start adopting the runtimes that edge compute platforms optimized for.
So there's that.
I think there's that developer desire.
There is the need for speed that Nick talked about.
I can confirm they've optimized their docs side beyond belief.
I was actually talking to one of the PlanetScale engineers and his deadline, his goal was 50
seconds.
Like, I'm really enjoying this conversation right now.
Awesome.
And the third one I want to add is cost.
So we're in an environment that is really tightening the belts of a lot of businesses.
And the edge might sound like a fancy new thing that adds to your expenses, but I would
argue that it's the opposite, right?
So number one, the compute runtimes that run edge workloads are cheaper.
They're optimized for really fast cold boots.
They scale to zero.
That's the case of edge functions and edge middleware on Vercel.
So they're fundamentally more cost effective.
And also going back to that analogy of like, you're adding that notch to the thread to
start processing the request earlier.
Now we have the opportunity to resolve the request from cached data.
This might sound small, but I talked to customers that have massive legacy backends or have
major agreements where they're paying by API call to their vendor.
So now if I'm caching at the edge while still being dynamic, because that's a killer feature,
I think, and personalized, now I'm reducing your backend bill.
Now with also technologies that would plan scale is bringing to market in terms of pushing
caches automatically closer to the user.
Now I'm hitting the core database workload less.
So the funny thing is that it's both exciting and a new toy for developers and improves
your efficiency as a business.
Yeah, this raises a question about whether this is the right design paradigm or design
approach for all applications.
And so surely this is the right decision for some, but it can't be, is it a panacea for
all of them?
Is this the final frontier of software infrastructure and all applications are going to be built
this way?
Like, where is this the right decision and where is this the wrong choice?
And I'll open this up to anyone.
I see Kurt smiling.
I'm also having a good laugh, but Kurt, go ahead.
I feel like this is the right choice for basically new apps with users.
It's not, and I think the interesting thing about internet infrastructure is that it's
almost additive.
And so it's not the right choice for existing clouds and existing workloads, but if you're
shipping an app that has humans use it, it's hard to argue that it's not the best way to
do it at this point in time.
And I think we're probably all pretty excited because there's a bigger market that doesn't
exist yet that's going to come from these things than there already is in the world.
So investors love to ask is probably like, well, what do you got to do to shift workloads
from existing things?
We just have to wait.
It'll happen.
So my hot take is it's absolutely the right choice for all apps with users right now.
And then the cold take is the interesting thing about compute, like localized compute
like this is if you have eyeballs, you tend to actually have a burst of compute needs
where the sun's up, but it also means you have a very cheap compute where it's dark
in the world.
So I think there's a lot of really interesting models for balancing workloads based on latency
sensitivity in both directions.
I think there's a chance to actually say this really doesn't need to be close to people,
so run it where it's cheap.
And I think we might start seeing a little bit of that on some platforms over the next
couple of years.
There was a comment earlier, I think it's Guillermo, who said that there's new languages
and frameworks that are more edge native.
So those workloads that are user facing and therefore under the definition put forth are
better suited for the edge.
Does that mean that people who have built applications in the old paradigm could rewrite
those in these edge native languages and frameworks?
Or is there a way to carry some of the stuff that some of my partners used decades ago
forward?
One thing to keep in mind is that the pendulum is swinging, maybe you can argue back to the
server from the client heavy applications, right?
So that this is the fundamental thing that we've been seeing for a number of years now,
but it's really becoming the default now, React server components.
React and create React app is to say, put all your logic on the client.
Now it's default server.
And if you're visualizing the pendulum swinging back, the pendulum is actually making a pit
stop at the edge before it goes to origin.
So that's what we mean when we mean edge first is push the code to the cloud in default to
try and put it as close as possible to the visitor.
But if not still put it in the cloud, because I would argue you get the better performance,
the size of the server is larger typically than the size of the client.
So it scales better with product maturity.
Imagine an app where you've added tons of feature flags, tons of components, tons of
styles, the single page application model, the client model just over time collapses
in its own weight, whereas there's plenty of space in the cloud.
So that's, I think one of the things that makes it such a good starting point.
You really have to look toward the future.
Sometimes it might seem like you can take the shortcut and say, oh, I can totally make
a client app here.
But I think you have to think about, okay, where's the product that you're on the line?
And the other thing I love about the edge is I get that control over the security of
the code and the cache invalidation and population.
So I don't have to worry about what state is the client in right now.
Are they seeing more information they should have if their administrator tweaked a permission
or a policy?
So because I have control over the edge and server environment, I can make more secure
applications.
That's the core argument I think for why not client.
I love your pendulum analogy and talking about kind of having a stop.
I think my maybe hot take, maybe just pragmatic take on this, I certainly view it as pragmatic
is that you can also swing that pendulum too far and kind of over engineer and over architect
yourself.
There are some data stores and there are some times where you have to make the round trip
to US East.
You have to make the round trip to the core data store, the API that powers your business.
And the goal of the edge is not to eliminate that.
The goal is to make it as fast as possible.
And the goal is to maybe minimize the time you have to do that.
But when we talk about, here at PlanetScale, we run a database.
We have really strict consistency and really strict policies about making sure we don't
lose data and things like that.
And so at times you kind of have to centralize on one server or a handful of servers located
in a data center.
And you can't get around that.
Now you can cache, you can incrementally move compute to the edge.
You can move cache data stores to the edge and you absolutely should do that.
But I'm a very pragmatic person.
And when I set out, I take a look at what my frameworks, what my deployment tools and
things like that are letting me do and pick kind of the right model for the right job.
Because you can't take shortcuts with resiliency.
You can't take shortcuts with consistency and things like that.
So pick the right task, pick the right place to put your data, to put your compute and
things like that.
And just understand that you don't have to be 100% over here, 100% over here.
You can run all of these frameworks in a old style, mainframe.
There's just one of them, just as easily as you can run them on the edge.
Now I wouldn't recommend going out and calling your IBM salesperson, but use the right tool
for the right job.
That's kind of my view on all of this.
It sounds simple, but it often isn't, especially when the technology is becoming much more
complicated for a good reason.
But it requires you to kind of learn a lot more and understand a lot more of what's going
on behind the scenes.
I actually love the consistency point.
I think that we're kind of talking about how devs have decided they want things to be fast
for their users.
And I think one thing that we've seen from devs over the last 10 plus years is they also
really thrive with strong consistency.
I think that if you're building an app and it has a database, it's much simpler to think
about things with strong consistency and to think about my right is going to happen and
it's going to be reflected.
And what's kind of neat, I think about what's happened with Edge right now, and what's neat
about developers driving this is it's not if you rewound eight, 12 years and wrote them
like red papers about how people thought this was going to work.
I think what they wouldn't have said is we're going to start pushing for SQLite as a database
for an app like Remix is doing, or PlanetScale is going to ship this excellent MySQL thing
that it's like a lot of old is new again.
I think the neat thing about, Chase, you're talking about your old apps is like a PHP
app with MySQL runs incredibly well at the Edge right now.
There's a model for this.
We're not like throwing a bunch of stuff out.
We're taking the stuff that makes sense for devs and has made sense.
And we've learned, we've tried out all these different things and in some ways gone back
and then also added these new capabilities to it, which is it makes the curmudgeon in
me really happy that like relational databases are still cool.
It's still a cool way to do stuff.
So I love the consistency point.
You mentioned SQLite, it would be remiss of us not to bring up DuckDB.
I mean, to anyone, talk to me, why is this exciting?
What's happening?
How are you leveraging that today?
Maybe, Kurt, take it.
I've been fiddling with DuckDB.
I'm really intrigued by kind of end process databases.
I think one of the things, Guillermo keeps pointing out or has pointed out that a lot
of this is shifting back from client to kind of server components.
And someone I work with, this is not a knock against PlanetScale.
I'm going to be very nice here.
I love PlanetScale.
I think MySQL is amazing and like we would use it for a lot of apps and a lot of customers
do.
But in some ways, one of the reasons CDNs exist in the form they exist in is because
the deployment model for WordPress was so terrible and MySQL is such a pain in the ass
for people to use.
And so we got to these static files that are very easy to send around.
I think the neat thing about things like DuckDB and SQLite and any other kind of end process
database is you can have a dynamic server side application that's almost as reliable
and almost as kind of resilient as a static site you put on a CDN.
Our holy grail for this is if you uploaded your 50 file static site to a CDN five years
ago and then you go load it today, it probably still works.
You haven't run out of RAM.
You haven't filled up a disk or anything like that.
And I think these embedded databases let you do, it's a little bit more like shipping a
spreadsheet around.
It lets you ship data and logic together in a way that I think extends that to make it
much more powerful than just the static site could have been.
I couldn't agree more, Kurt.
And for what it's worth, I'm under no auspices that MySQL is not difficult to use.
That's in fact, if it were too easy, I'm not sure we'd have a business.
So by all means, don't run your own MySQL, use PlanetScale instead.
But one piece of that, and I really love the kind of shipping a spreadsheet and the logic,
and this is exactly how I think about it.
Durability and consistency again is very hard.
So the simpler you can make the data model at the very back end, the easier it is for
you to maintain that durability and consistency.
The easier it is for you to ship all of that to the edge and say, let's let an edge function
on a very fast server, just pull the raw data in.
It's much faster than kind of doing all of that computing super far away.
And then let's ship that with a DuckDB to the user, let them modify and actually run
this dashboard right in their browser with a server 20 milliseconds away.
Whenever they click save, sure, you have to send all of that data back.
And we understand that's a round trip around the world, but you get this beautiful interactive
browser experience or application experience, and all you have to do is talk to the edge.
So again, that's why I love the string analogy.
The more that you can keep a user interaction on the shortest string possible, the better
you'll be.
And knowing at the end of the day, there's this long string out there that you have to
use, but let's try and make it as short as possible as often as possible.
I wanted to paint a picture because I really agree with Kurt, where he mentioned that a
lot of folks assumed that the best cloud database that we could get is putting stock MySQL in
some container or VBS somewhere.
And then they thought I must add more layers, more complexity in order to scale that.
But now imagine for a second that that idea that the database doesn't scale goes away.
Like how much simpler does the cloud get if I have databases like PlanetScale or Neon
that just scale?
Of course they have consumption based models and things like that.
Anytime something scales, it costs money, of course.
But I think it's remarkable because the reason that we're seeing that pendulum swing back
as well is that I think inside of all of us, there is a PHP developer that longs for, I'm
just opening a tag and writing my SQL query to PlanetScale.
And maybe that evolves into like it's React server components now.
But just the simplicity of that model is so compelling.
And you think now we've figured out how to scale those databases.
Sam, the CEO of PlanetScale was at GitHub where, I mean, all of GitHub and it's bazillion
dollar business runs on Vtes in MySQL.
And there was a ton of learnings on how to scale that, but now that's being offered as
a service and Vercel Developer can install that database with one click.
So I'm really excited about just how easy we're making scaling to remarkable sizes and
also getting started in like a couple of seconds.
So I'm really excited about SQLite and DuckDB, but I think it's also worth pointing out that
we're now dealing with a new generation of databases that have been built for the cloud
and it's worth trying them out.
We have a special guest in the audience today.
I invited Chad GPT and posed a question.
I seriously did this.
I actually said, here are the people who are talking, what questions do you have for them?
This is the question that came back.
How do you handle data replication and consistency across multiple edge locations?
And I think, well, props to them and our friends at OpenAI, but I think this fits into the
discussion nicely because there are definitely use cases where you can ship the spreadsheet
quote unquote to the user alongside the computer.
But there are also use cases where you need some sort of eventual consistency for some
data that is being accumulated or stored somewhere else just through the nature of that application.
And so what are the situations where data needs to be...
Will data always be near the user or will we always have this centralized cap theorem
challenge?
I'm happy to start off.
And I think the fact of the matter is that sometimes the data is going to be far away
from the user.
This actually used to be an interview question of mine that I would ask, but imagine you're
using Google or Facebook or a big website.
You're at JFK in New York, you're about to board a plane to Paris.
You post something, you hop on the plane and you get off nine hours later.
How can your data be closer to you there?
Facebook doesn't know you're going to Paris.
It has no idea.
So you have to implement some sort of system where you either move the data closer to the
user when they use it or you have to start calling back from far away.
But at the end of the day, the one thing that we all can't solve is, would that we could
here at PlanetScale, would that we would anywhere, is that when computers synchronize and when
you get the level of consistency that some applications require, you've got to have two
computers talk to each other.
And those two computers may have to talk to each other from far away.
So there's a whole lot of work that you can do to optimize that.
There are great data stores.
There are great kind of systems for doing this.
But ultimately, the cost to really synchronize and the cost to really kind of get the level
of consistency, availability and durability that you need.
You do have to have some computers talk to each other across the Internet and you do
have to at least pay a little bit of cost in order for that to happen across geographies.
Or you end up with a situation where it's more eventual than consistent.
And users will notice that, right?
Users expect that when they click post and they refresh, that post is there.
So there are some kind of things that you just can't avoid.
The trick, I think, is that Edge and kind of all of this new technology gives you the
ability to avoid that in the 90 percent case.
Whereas before you're paying your worst cost every request, now you're only doing that
when you absolutely need to.
And that's, I think, that's really the secret sauce when we talk about a lot of this.
To add to that, the way that I think about Vercel a lot in terms of our Edge infrastructure
is that more so the compute layer, we're basically like a global distributed key value store
that has a lot of facilities for caching, invalidating those caches and distributing
the knowledge that those caches have been invalidated at planet scale.
So I think to your point, the Edge and adding this ability to cache closer to the user whenever
the eventually consistent data model fits.
Now it turns out it fits for a lot of really high traffic events, right?
Like whether it's that you're going to some e-commerce website during Black Friday and
there's a bunch of data that doesn't need to be fetched from origin, right?
Like the product description.
Now there's a caveat from like the old days of the legacy CDN, right?
Like I might be fetching data that has been already filtered down and personalized for
me.
It might be because I'm in California and I get the offers for California, or it might
be a certain promotion, or it might be the CMS content that's been A/B tested, but all
of that can basically be hoisted and be stored temporarily or for a longer duration as close
as possible to the visitor.
But then there is the harder problems of like, if I have an internal app, if I have a feed,
so going to that Facebook example or the Twitter example, it gets harder to cache that data.
You might actually be stale and I want to know exactly how many likes I have right now.
So I think it really depends on each type of application, what we can do and what possibilities
the Edge opens up in terms of global data.
Yeah, I think that makes a ton of sense.
I think the interesting thing about the apps developers are building is we look at something
like PlanetScale and think, "Hey, this is useful for most apps."
It's kind of like a universally useful thing to put behind applications.
But I think one of the most interesting things about data as people start building things
around the world is when you kind of break out of that for very specific purposes.
So I talk about game servers all the time.
It's such a great model because in some ways Edge gets really interesting when you have
two users that want to kind of share a memory space basically, which is a way you would
implement a game server, do like very high volume events that are built Figma basically.
And a lot of the trick then becomes it's strings.
And what you end up doing is you have a person in London and a person in Sydney, and then
you end up wanting to connect them to a server in Chicago because that's the most optimal
place to attach them around the world.
And their apps still using PlanetScale, but you start busting out and coming up with these
kind of things that aren't quite databases, but involve persistence, involve sharing data,
I think are really fascinating.
And this is why one of the hottest things you'll hear about at conferences now is things
like CRDTs because what we're learning is all of these little tricks for managing eventual
consistency, propagating changes as fast as we can to where people are nearby, and then
ultimately having it land in MySQL basically.
And so the data problem is fun.
Real world example of this I think is you may have one centralized database for users,
usernames, passwords, profile information, and things like that.
That does have to be consistent.
You kind of want one source of truth.
You don't want your record of who a person is to be eventually consistent, but can you
build a system that once a user's logged in, they're given a token or some sort of cryptographically
secure piece of information that lets them act in the system without having to go validate
it back at that database for every page load.
If you can build a system like that, then all of a sudden you can connect two users
on the shortest path, totally remove that data store from the system and let them have
a great time.
When they come back and make some sort of update or something like that, the administrative
action kind of goes back, but you really have to think about every single action.
What data do I have and what data do I need?
If you can leverage the edge with kind of no preconceptions about that, you can really
go a lot farther than you could 10 years ago where it just didn't matter and you really
didn't have to think about it.
You are rendering HTML on the server side right next to the database.
Who cares about how many database queries you're running?
It's all right there.
That world is just over.
Yeah, you're on my mind, Nick, because I wanted to share two product requirements where we're
starting to give people more specialized ways of storing data.
So the vast majority of data might be in planet scale, but for example, I like to use the
example of when Apple says the new iPhone is coming, we're putting a facade over the
store.
We're really disabling the store to create some intrigue and whatever, something is coming.
We can model that as a globally replicated data point that can be modified at runtime.
So we call this edge config.
So when you make a change to the edge config, we push it actively to every place in the
world where we can run compute.
So now when I'm rendering my pages, say if store closed, render some FOMO inducing illustration
else here's all the items.
And I can control that flag without redeploying my application and without going all the way
to origin.
So I'm truly doing everything and personalizing everything at the edge.
So with edge config on Vercel, you get that extra layer on top of data, that extra knob
to be able to compliment your core data store or your core backends.
And the other one that we're thinking about is the one that Nick mentioned where the product
example here is your shopping cart state.
Whether you have three things, imagine you're anonymously compiling a wishlist or your card
before you log into Amazon.
Do you really need to go to origin in order to collect those items into the store, into
your bag?
Probably not.
It's just for that user.
It can travel the world with that user and it can offer consistency for that user without
going to origin.
So I think we're going to see more of the emergence of these specialized data stores
and DuckDB and others may be examples of this.
It's clear from this discussion that data replication consistency is hard.
Abstraction definitely helps here.
So let's talk about serverless.
I feel like recently serverless, edge, the terms are being used a little bit interchangeably.
Why is this happening?
Should they be interchangeable?
Maybe one for you, cut.
Oh boy.
I have hot takes about serverless.
I don't, so like if we skip the hot takes for a second, I think that when people are
sort of legitimately talking about serverless, when it's not just a marketing thing, and
I think so much of this has been informed by like AWS shipping Lambda and then inventing
a way to use it, which was not entirely organic.
I think what happens, and Guillermo mentioned this when he said scaling to zero.
I think what happens when you do push compute and push logic and push apps all over the
world is all of a sudden you start caring a lot about what's turned on and when.
And I think when people are talking about serverless, a lot of it is like, I obviously
am not going to keep 140 processes running all around the world at all times.
I'm obviously not going to keep 140 replicas of my entire database all around the world
at all times.
And I think that it's not that they're interchangeable, it's that the truly interesting serverless
stuff is very important for global workloads.
And I think that it almost always reduces to when is my stuff running versus when is
it not, and when do I have data somewhere and when do I don't.
And a lot on top of that is not entirely useful all of the time.
Yeah, I would say when you want to go global first and you might be using an older deployment
model, it's hard to justify the cost, right?
Like, okay, so I'm going to be in 20 data centers.
I'm going to create 20 Kubernetes clusters and 20 data stores.
I like that example, Kurt.
Most folks don't want to do that.
So I think Edge has inherited a lot of the properties of serverless in that in order
to make the dream viable of deploying a dynamic workload that has a similar cost model and
operational model as a static CDN, but it can execute dynamic compute.
Those things typically go hand in hand, the ability to scale to zero, the ability to scale
up really quickly.
This one's really interesting.
We have a lot of customers in the media streaming space and some of the tech leaders tell me
I have, we drop a new episode that might become extremely popular in one specific region of
the world.
Sometimes it's completely unpredictable.
There's just folks that tend to like some shows and some episodes more.
So they need, they can't even predict where to preallocate more compute.
So they need that ability to spike up and scale up really, really quickly in a very
uncertain environment, very unpredictable environment.
So I think it's not just a scale to zero is the rapid fluctuations in traffic.
Yeah, I couldn't agree more.
And, you know, I'll add one small hot take.
I'm often fond of saying internally that we put the server in serverless.
You know, we've got customers that were onboarding at the terabyte, the petabyte scale of data,
and those people know they have servers.
They want to know how many, they want to know how much they cost.
That's a big portion of what we provide is actually the ability to talk about servers.
And so I I've used serverless as a similar phrase to agile or rest or other words that
people in the industry use to describe a thought process or to describe a framework with which
they're operating their business.
When you say I do agile, what you really mean is I don't plan too far and ahead, but I understand
we're going to make mistakes and we have to kind of be iterative when people say they
do rest.
What they really mean is they make HTTP requests and get Jason back.
They're not talking about the entire framework.
And so to me, you can do serverless without an edge.
You can have Lambda in one region that does one thing and it's incredibly slow with really
cold starts and doesn't have any of the properties that you actually want out of an edge.
Or you can kind of adopt the serverless best practices.
You can use the right framework, you can use the right tools and you can go incredibly
far.
So to me, I think we've just outgrown the term.
We need to combine a lot of different pieces of what we're talking about.
Maybe call it like, you know, like we have 13 factor apps, you've got the 13 factor serverless
application that uses the edge optimistically, that caches optimistically and kind of all
the things that we've discussed.
But at the end of the day, just saying serverless now is not necessarily going to give people
the information they need to understand what it is you're actually trying to do.
And I'm a pragmatic person, so I'm always trying to drill in.
What are people really trying to do with PlanetScale?
What are people really trying to do with their database?
And to me, saying serverless at this point is akin to saying it's fast.
It's like, cool, yes, we all want it to be fast.
But what is it actually?
What is your serverless really doing?
When you can bust through that, that's when you can have these nuanced technical discussions
about how to design beautiful experiences for customers.
But just saying serverless isn't enough to get there.
So I will take this video and I will send it to AWS's product marketing department so
you can take care of this confusion.
We need to end it.
Maybe this next question is a little bit of a call to arms.
What are some of the things that have yet to be solved for this design paradigm?
If I'm a builder, I'm a developer building some application that is user-facing, what
needs to be there that's not there today?
I was going to say for the first part of the question, what do developers, how do developers
adopt best of breed technologies today?
I would say our point of view is this idea of framework defined infrastructure because
to Nick's point, it's very hard to adopt a very nebulous term like serverless.
And edge for a lot of folks is also quite nebulous.
So if serverless for you means fast and flexible infrastructure and iterate quickly, I like
the agile comparison because I do think a lot of folks just want to become more agile
as a business.
And that's why they are attracted to serverless.
I would say, start with a framework, a modern framework has been designed in conjunction
with a platform or with infrastructure that allows you to get that agility.
So obviously for us, it's Next.js and Vercel or it's VeltKit or Remix or Astro.
This modern frameworks tend to bake in best practices and opinions to get a lot of the
benefits that you want out of this new trends.
Maybe the last question we have for everyone.
What questions do you have for each other?
Are there any burning questions you have from before this call or from during this call
that you want to learn from each other about the open forum?
I think we talk a lot.
I was going to say the same thing.
I was going to say it's a friendly group of faces.
The thing that I'm always curious about is we all own a slice of the stack, let's say.
Some bigger slices, some smaller slices, some deeper, but at the end of the day, none of
us are the one-stop shop for a customer.
You're not only going to go to fly.
You're not only going to go to Vercel or PlanetScale.
What are the pieces that you see your customers struggling with outside of your slice?
Where are they failing?
Oftentimes that failure can cascade, and we see this all the time.
That failure cascades to they're spending less money on PlanetScale.
They're consuming fewer database resources.
I wish I could snap my fingers and give them what to actually make them more successful
on your platform.
Juan, I love that you set it up that way.
I think that you can't send this next bar to AWS.
I think if you fast forward 10, 15 years, the next public cloud is kind of a rebel alliance
of us three and 47 other companies that have basically built a very special user experience
for a deep problem that actual humans have versus cobbling together 400 products with
wildly variable experiences that might occasionally be good.
I actually love your question because I think it's like, "Well, one, that sounds great for
all of us.
That's amazing if all future workloads are in some combination of these platforms."
But I think what's so interesting is there's still silos.
It's hard to get a cohesive developer experience that actually does everything someone would
need to do.
I think you can pick and choose and get good pieces.
And if you know which companies to go talk to and you know which products to go use,
you can actually build the 15-year from now stack right now.
But you still have to know this.
And I think what's been interesting about watching people push this in different directions,
and we have a very different set of users than Vercel, I feel like Vercel solves a big
problem for a lot of people.
I feel like we solve a big problem for a lot of different people.
And I think ultimately those two groups intersect at some point.
And I'm not sure how we make that good, how we make this cohesive, how we make it so someone's
not looking at Amazon's 250 products.
These numbers will be different every time I say it, 250-plus products.
And then comparing it to our one thing that we're exceptionally good at and giving it
a good shake, basically.
So that's what I'm most interested in figuring out with these guys and 50 other friends,
basically.
Yeah.
Something you mentioned there too is when the complexity accumulates, maintaining a
cohesive developer experience over time becomes quite the feat.
So this is a problem space that we're looking at quite closely now, which is what we've
noticed is we can bake in all the best possible best practices and recommendations and ideas
that we can into the platform and into the frameworks.
But at some point, these frameworks are Turing complete.
They can do everything.
They can mine Bitcoin if you want.
And I'm not saying employees out there, a massive enterprise that are deploying Bitcoin
mining scripts.
But because the power is unlimited, how do you guide organizations of really sizable
scale into the right patterns?
Whether it's, okay, planet scale is going to be fast by default, but if you forget to
use an index or you do a crazy left join, whatever, like, oh, there's going to be a
price there.
And how do folks inside an organization negotiate those trade-offs and even the awareness that
they're making those trade-offs and accumulating that tech that.
So I think there is a lot to be solved beyond the world of infrastructure.
It's more like the developer experience at scale and more importantly, over time, everyone
launches something new and it's fast and cool on day one.
What's the DX in day 100?
That's the problem that we're looking at now and it's a tough one, but we're excited about
it.
I couldn't agree.
Oh, sorry.
Go ahead.
I actually love that you brought that up.
I think one, I'm kind of constantly at risk of feeling curmudgeonly, but one of the, I
think interesting things about developers now versus 10 plus years ago is there's, I
felt there's this almost like resistance to understanding the plumbing.
That makes sense.
And I don't really know what the answer there is, but when you talk about things like missing
an index or even if you go as far as how do you debug an app that's successful, deploy
it over the world and actually identify where it's not doing what you want, even if it's
behaving the way the infrastructure thinks it should.
I've been very curious what people were going to need to know in 10 years when they're working
with this stuff.
Because part of me is you should learn the plumbing.
It's great.
It makes your life better.
It's reasonable in some ways.
Yeah.
I'll add on one more.
I completely agree with you about knowing the plumbing.
I think every, at every layer here, you can get yourself in a great situation or a really
difficult situation just by kind of holding it wrong.
And that's a problem.
The thing that I'll add on is I think the enterprise and a lot of what we're talking
about here are still smaller teams, people picking and choosing the cutting edge as we
get farther into the enterprise.
And we've had a lot of fun doing that.
Compliance, security, kind of pleasing internal security teams.
I think we give teams heart attack when we talk about, oh, it can be global.
You can be anywhere.
And the first thing on someone who, mine, whose job it is to manage risk goes, what
are you talking about?
I know firewalls.
I know networking rules.
I know subnets.
And that's no fault to them because that's how technology's worked.
How do you sell into a company like that who you know can move so much faster and actually
gain a competitive advantage while at the same time they're doing two levels up in terms
of developer tooling and paradigms, bridging that gap with all of these and 50 other companies
is really difficult.
And it's something that Amazon does well, right?
Once you buy into the Amazon, you've got the Amazon, you can use any of those 400 different
pieces.
We all have to figure out our own part of that stack and how to sell our part of that
stack and marry those parts together in a way that is compliant and understandable so
that these bigger companies can kind of understand it and see through it with pricing and all
of that.
Points to this idea that perhaps partnerships between companies like the ones you all are
building is the most important feature developer experience.
And so now that we've mentioned Bitcoin, DuckDB and AI and Edge, I think we've hit all the
things that matter today.
And so our work is done here.
Thank you all for having this discussion.
We will be posting this for the rest of the world who wasn't here live to see.
And this is wonderful.
Thank you.
Thank you so much.
Thanks, everyone.
Have a good one, everyone.
Bye, everyone.
Bye.
[ Silence ]